根据萨罗·布莱尔利的书籍
《漫漫回家路》改编
根据真实故事改编
萨罗
Saroo.
快  快跑
Come on, come on!
上来
Get up!
快点  抓紧了  萨罗  抓住
Come on, quickly! Hold it properly, Saroo, catch!
下去
Get down!
古度  守卫追来了
Guddu! The guards!
嘿  小子  快下来
Hey, boy, get down!
下来  小子
Go! Get down, boy!
印度  坎德瓦
-萨罗  -古度
- Saroo. - Guddu.
萨罗
Saroo.
我来了
I'm here!
我们今天能得到很多钱
We will get a lot of money today
我们偷到了很多煤
We've got a lot of coal!
给我看看
Show me!
这么多啊
Ohhh, so much!
你总是说我很小  但你看我多聪明
You kept telling me how little I am but see how clever I am?
没错  你的确很聪明
That's right, you are!
你从那么高的地方跳下去了  真了不起
You jumped from so high! What a leap!
是啊  真的很高
Yes, great heights!
给他们些牛奶  两袋
Give them some milk, two packets
古度  我想吃糖耳朵
Guddu, I want some jalebis!
总有一天  我会给你买很多糖耳朵
One day I will buy you some jalebis
我们把整家店都买下来
We'll buy the whole shop!
哈哈  好的
Ha, alright
-现在应该走哪边  -左边
- Which way should I go now? - Left, left!
-现在呢  -右边
- Which way now?  - Right, right
你想喝牛奶吗
Do you want to drink some milk?
我搞到牛奶了哦
I got some milk!
简直是魔法
It's magic
告诉我  你们是怎么搞到牛奶的
Tell me now how did you get the milk?
说实话哦
Be honest
古度  萨罗
Guddu? My Saroo?
我不喝
No
好了  夏绮拉  我得工作了
Okay, Shekila, I have to work now
谁来照顾夏绮拉
Who's going to look after Shekila?
我的萨罗
My Saroo?
来  吃吧
Come, eat
睡吧  睡吧
Sleep... sleep
你要离开多久
How long will you be away for?
你今天做得很棒
You did a really good job today
我也想去
I want to come too
-要多少天  -我要去一周
- How many days? - I'm going for a week
-谁来照顾夏绮拉  -卡鲁会的
- Who's going to look after Shekila?  - Kallu will be here
-你太小了  扛不动包  -我可以扛得动任何东西
- You're too small to lift bales  - I can lift anything
古度
Guddu!
我能一起去吗
Can I come too?
你太小了  做不了这种事
You're too small, you can't do this
我能扛得动任何东西
I can lift anything
萨罗  我跟你说过了
Saroo, I've told you
那是夜班工作  小孩子干不了
it's night work, not for kids
走吧  你太小了
Go, go, you're too small
萨罗  放下吧
Saroo, leave it
我还能扛得动这个
I can lift this
好吧  行
Okay, fine
嘿  古度
Hey, Guddu!
嘿  你还好吗  山卡
Hey! How are you, Shankar?
-萨罗  快  醒醒  -我想睡觉
- Saroo, come on, wake up now!  - I want to sleep
-萨罗  醒醒  -我想睡觉
- Saroo, wake up!  - I want to sleep
-萨罗  -我想睡觉
- Saroo  - I want to sleep
-萨罗  醒醒  -别烦我  我在睡觉呢
- Saroo, wake up  - Don't annoy me, I am sleeping
都是我的错  是我把你带来的
It's my fault, I brought you here
你太小了  做不了夜班工作
You're too young for the night work
真的很晚才开工  你永远没法工作
It's so late you will never be able to work
萨罗  萨罗
Saroo, Saroo...
我去看看工作的事  好吗
I'm going to find out about work, okay?
我等下就回来
And then I'll come back
你在这里等着  别到处乱跑
You wait here, don't go anywhere
古度
Guddu?
给我买回一百个糖耳朵哦
Just bring back a hundred jalebis
你想吃糖耳朵
You want jalebis?
-给我买回两百个糖耳朵  -糖耳朵
- Bring me two thousand jalebis! - Jalebis?
你就在这等着  别乱跑
Just wait there, don't go anywhere
古度
Guddu?
救救我
Help me!
古度  古度
Guddu! Guddu!
快来人救救我
Someone save me!
救救我
Help me!
Help!
古度
Guddu!
妈  我很爱你
Mum, I love you very much
古度  我很想你
Guddu, I miss you very much
2号站台的列车是一辆退役列车
The train on platform two is a decommissioned train
不再载客
It is not taking passengers
救救我
Save me!
快来人救救我
Someone help me!
放我出去
Get me out of here!
救救我
Save me...
放我出去  救救我
Get me out of here! Save me!
救救我  救救我
Save me! Save me!
西孟加拉邦  加尔各答
位于坎德瓦以东1600公里处
开门
Open!
古度
Guddu!
妈妈
Mum!
古度
Guddu!
妈妈
Mum!
甘尼斯塔莱
Ganestalay?
我想回家  我家在甘尼斯塔莱
I want to go home, Ganestalay
甘尼斯塔莱
Ganestalay?
甘尼斯塔莱  我想回家
Ganestalay? I want to go home
我听不懂  说孟加拉语  我听不懂你在说什么
I don't understand! Speak Bengali! I don't understand you
让开  搞什么  你听不懂孟加拉语吗
Move! What's the matter? You don't understand Bengali?
甘尼斯塔莱
Ganestalay?
别在那上面走  你会掉下来的
Don't walk on that, you're going to fall off
-你听得懂印地语吗  -是的
- Do you understand Hindi? - Yes
-你要去哪儿  -我得回家  我迷路了
- Where are you going? - I have to go home, I am lost
-你是从这边来的吗  -我也不知道
- Did you come from this way or that? - I don't know which way
那你怎么回家
Then how will you go?
-你叫什么名字  -萨罗
- What's your name? - Saroo
我叫诺奥
My name is Noor
你饿了吗
You're hungry?
来吧
Come on
进来吧  快点
Come inside, come on!
来吧
Come on!
我不得不做这些
I have to do all this
给男人们做午餐盒饭
make lunch boxes for all the men.
人总得填饱肚子
You have to feed your stomach, you know.
每个人都得工作
Everybody has to work
我会帮我妈搬石头
I help my mum to carry rocks
你妈妈是搬石头的
Your mum carries rocks?
瞧这是什么
What is this?
喝吧
Just drink
给我留点哦
Leave some for me!
抹点肥皂
And now a bit of soap
有个叫罗摩的人  他是个大好人
There is a man and he is called Rama he's a very good man
他帮助所有人  肯定也会帮助你的
He helps everyone, he will help you too
他明天早上会过来
He's coming tomorrow morning
他会帮我找到我妈吗
Is he going to help me look for my mum?
他会帮助你找到你妈
He's going to help you look for your mum
闭上眼睡觉吧
Close your eyes go to sleep
睡吧
Sleep
我的宝贝
Oh, my baby
你在睡觉吗
Were you sleeping?
我很好奇你是从多远的地方漂泊来的
I wonder what worlds you've travelled.
-你是罗摩吗  -是的  但不是那个神
- Are you Rama? - Yes, but not the God
来躺下吧
Come and lie down
靠近点
Come closer
你知道吗  我是从很远的地方来见你的
Do you know? I've come to meet you from really far away
我想带你去一个好地方
and I want to take you to a really nice place
你会带我去找我妈吗
Are you going to take me to Mum?
从哪里  我们会试着去找你妈
And from there we're going to try and look for your mum
我今晚回来  然后我们就去找
I'll be back tonight and then we'll search.
起来
Get up!
靠近点
Come closer
说"谢谢"
Say "thank you"
谢谢
Thank you.
你做得很好
You've done well
他完全是我们想找的类型
He's exactly what they're looking for.
怎么了  你没喝吗
What happened? You didn't drink?
你不喜欢吗
You don't like it?
你怎么不高兴
Why are you down?
喝下吧
Drink this
靠近点
Come closer.
萨罗
Saroo!
好孩子
Good boy!
去搬小点的
Go pick up the small ones
好孩子
Good boy!
好孩子  真是好孩子
Good boy! Good boy!
好孩子
Good boy!
谁是我的好孩子  是谁啊
Who's my good boy? Who is it?
对不起  妈妈
I'm sorry, Mum
两个月后
我从餐厅出来  开始跟他说话
So I came out of the cafe and started talking to him
我意识到他根本不会说孟加拉语
I realized he doesn't speak a word of Bengali
他只会说印地语
He only speaks Hindi
我就问他来自什么地方
I asked him where he was from?
他只会回答一个词  叫甘尼斯塔莱
He replied with only one word "Ganestalay"
我从没听说过
I've never heard of it
甘尼斯塔莱
Ganestalay
听着  甘尼斯塔莱位于哪个区
Okay, which district is Ganestalay in?
甘尼斯塔莱位于哪个区
Which district is Ganestalay in?
-你母亲叫什么 -妈妈
- What is your mother's name?  - Mum
-你叫什么名字  -阿米塔
- What's your name? - Amita
这是个很可怕的地方
This is a very bad place
有人可以离开这里吗
Does anybody ever leave here?
我见到过
I've seen it
-你离开以后要干什么  -我要买个手表
- What are you going to do once you leave? - I'm going to buy a watch
你们写了吗
Did you write it?
喂  尚迪普  你在干什么
Hey, Shonedeep! What are you doing?
停下
Stop!
-停下  立刻停下  -尚迪普
- Stop! Stop right now! - Shonedeep!
你为什么这么淘气
Why are you being so naughty?
尚迪普
Shonedeep!
给我过来  我要好好打你一顿
Come with me, I'm going to give you a good beating!
你休想逃脱惩罚
You won't get away with this!
尚迪普  起来  快点
Shonedeep! Come on, come on!
尚迪普  起来
Shonedeep! Come on!
看这边  看这边
Look this way, look this way
是我  没事  我带他走
It's me, it's okay, I'll take him
明天天亮前把他送回来
Bring him back before morning
星星都出来  寻找月亮
All the stars came out in search of the moon
命运悲惨的人都来到大街上
The ill-fated came out on the streets
星星都出来  寻找月亮
All the stars came out in search of the moon
它们出来寻找贼
They came out in search of the thief
星星都出来了
The stars came out
萨罗  我是苏德太太  来坐下
Yes, Saroo, my name is Mrs. Sood, come sit here
我的任务就是确保
It's my job to make sure that
只要孩子们能有别的去处  就不要在这里遭罪
there isn't a single kid here who should be somewhere else
所以我才会来这里
That's why I'm here
这里的人都不喜欢我
People don't like me here
看看这个
Look at this
我们已经打听你的来历很长时间了
We have been asking around about you for a long time.
我们在报纸上刊登了启事
We have published it in the newspaper
在加尔各答所有的报纸上都刊登了
In all the newspapers in Calcutta
有1500万人看了这报纸  那可是很多人
15 million people read this paper, that's a lot of people.
但却没有收到任何回复
But we haven't had a single reply
我家在很远的地方
My home is really far
一个回复都没有
Not one reply
-我妈妈也没回复吗  -没有
- What about Mum? - No
你妈妈也没有
Not even Mum
古度呢
Guddu?
萨罗
Saroo...
澳大利亚有一户人家
We have found a family over in Austral
愿意照顾你
who want to look after you
你知道澳大利亚在哪儿吗
Do you know where Australia is?
你想看看他们吗
Would you like to see them?
来  我指给你看
Come, I'll show you
来坐着
Come sit here
你看这个  这是约翰
Look, look at this, this is John
这是苏
and this is Sue
这个...
This...
这是他们的家
This is their home
他们住在塔斯马尼亚岛
They live in Tasmania
那是个小岛  那里的人都很好
A small island and everyone there is really nice
他们看上去都很好  不是吗
They are such nice people! Aren't they?
这个你拿着  好好保管  好吗
Keep this with you and keep it safe, ok?
萨罗
Saroo...
孩子  你不能待在这里
Son, you can't stay here
你真的帮我找我妈妈了吗
Did you really look for my mum?
到处找过了
Looked everywhere
你将会拥有一个美好的家
You'll have a nice home
澳大利亚是个好地方
Australia is a great place
每个人都有一张布巾吗
Does everybody have a napkin?
-这叫餐巾  -餐巾
- This is called a "serviette" - Serviette
像这样铺在腿上
Lay it down on your lap like this
食物就不会掉在你的衣服上
so that food doesn't fall on your clothes.
也不会毁了你的衣服
So it doesn't ruin them
我会教你们怎么用西式餐具吃饭
I'm going to teach you how to eat using cutlery
我会问你们
I will ask you,
每样东西用英语怎么说
and you will tell me in English what each thing is called
这个怎么说
What do you call this?
叉子
Fork.
叉子  没错  很好
Fork. Yes good.
-那这个叫什么  -"好子"
- What do you call this? - Nice
是刀子
Knife.
很好
Good.
那这个呢
And this?
勺子  勺子
Spoon. Spoon.
好了  曼尼莎  你来告诉我  这叫什么
Okay, Manisha, you tell me, what is this?
好好想想
Try to remember
盐  盐
Salt. Salt.
非常好
Very good.
福椒粉
Payper!
-是胡椒粉  -胡椒粉
- Pepper. - Pepper.
胡椒粉
Pepper.
好的  好的
Okay, okay.
澳大利亚  霍巴特
谢谢
Thank you.
萨罗
Saroo.
这就是你的爸爸妈妈了
This is your mum and dad
去打个招呼
Say hello
你好  我是索米娅
Hello, I'm Swarmina.
你好  我是约翰  这位是苏
Oh hello. I'm John, this is Sue.
你好啊
Hello there.
你好  这是送给你的
Hello. Here this is for you.
一路飞来还好吧  还好吗
Good on the plane? Eh, good?
苏
Sue...
-她是  -妈妈和...
- This is... - Mummy and...
爸爸
Dad.
我们很高兴能见到你
And we're so happy to meet you.
一艘船
A boat.
太棒了
Amazing.
放松  放松
Gently... gently...
这就是你住的地方
This is where you live.
在那边  那是客厅
Down there, that's the living room.
那是电视
Television.
你知道电视是什么吗
Do you know what a television is?
可以播放画面
Pictures.
水
Water.
你可以打开它
You can open it.
你觉得我应该帮他撕开吗
Do you want me to cut it up for him?
福椒粉
Payper!
什么
What was it?
福椒粉
Payper!
没错  胡椒粉  说得对  这个呢...
Yes, pepper. That's right and...
-酱料  -酱料
- Sauce! - Sauce?
-是盐  -盐
- Salt. - Salt.
非常好啊
Very good.
嗨
Hi.
你经历了很多事才来到这里  对吧
So, you've come a long way, haven't you? Hmm?
小家伙
Little one.
我相信那一定很不容易
I'm sure it hasn't been easy.
有一天你会告诉我一切的
One day you will tell me all about it.
你会告诉我所有  你是谁  关于你的一切
You'll tell me everything. Who you are, everything.
我永远都会聆听的
I'll always listen.
永远
Always.
一年后
保持不动  没错
Stay, yeah yeah...
没错  就是这样
Yeah, that's... that's it.
-手下留情  好吗  -没错
- Go easy on me, yeah? - Yeah.
来吧伙计
Okay mate.
-妈妈  爸爸  -集中注意
- Mum... Daddy... - Pay attention.
他要投了  来吧伙计
Here he comes! Come on mate!
她出局了
She's out!
我的天啊
Oh my gosh!
你们怎么能这么对我
How did you do this to me?
好了
All right.
爸爸  妈妈  萨罗
Dad, mum, Saroo...
曼塔希
Mantosh.
是的
Yes.
又见面了
Hello again!
萨罗  我的天啊  快看看你
Aw, Saroo, my goodness, look at you!
你好
Hi.
我的天啊  我们非常激动
Oh my gosh, we've been so excited!
这是曼塔希
This is Mantosh.
你好
Hi.
你好  曼塔希
Hey Mantosh...
这是萨罗  我叫苏
This is Saroo. I'm Sue...
这是萨罗  你的哥哥
This is Saroo, your brother.
-他是约翰  -你好啊  伙计
- And John... - Hello mate!
快给曼塔希看看你的礼物
Show, show Mantosh what you've done.
他画了幅画
He did a picture, Yeah...
-坐了很久的飞机吧  -是的  是的
- It's been a long flight? - Yes, Yes, Yes.
你一定饿了
You must be hungry.
我们要去吃点东西
We're going to get something to eat.
你想和我们一起吗
Would you... like to join us?
好的  那真是太好了
Oh alright, ok that would be nice.
快停下  快停下
Stop, stop, stop, stop...
不要这样  没事的  我知道  没事的
No no no, It's alright. I know it's Okay.
停下  快停下
Stop it! Stop it! Stop it! Stop!
-快来  -我知道  我知道
- Come on... - I know I know...
-不  不要  -小家伙
- No no no. - Hey mate.
没事  去玩玩具吧
It's okay. Just play with your toys.
不  不  不要打了  伙计
No, no, no, don't hit mate.
不要打自己了  别打脑袋  别打脑袋
Don't hit yourself. No no no.. Not your head.. Not your head.
-好了  -你没事了  没事了
- Come on - You're alright, you're alright...
没事了
It's okay.
没事的  伙计
Come on, it's okay, man.
看  那有艘船  现在好多了
Look, there's a boat. It's better now.
我没事
I'm okay.
我没事的
I'm all right .
20年后
-我们会想你的  -好啦
- We're gonna miss you. - Yeah.
只是去墨尔本而已
It's only Melbourne.
是谁要漂洋过海了
Who is across the water?
萨罗
Saroo...
我们漂亮的孩子
Our beautiful boy!
希望这能满足你的一切期望
May this bring you all that you could wish for.
是啊  并且还不止呢
Yeah, and then some.
谢谢妈妈  谢谢爸爸
Thanks mum. Thanks dad.
从你进入我们生命中的那一刻
From the moment you came into our lives...
-妈妈  -不  不  让我说完
- Mum... - No no no, let me finish.
从你进入我们生命中的那一刻
From the moment you came into our lives...
你满足了我们所有的期望
You were all that we could have hoped for.
甚至超出了我们的期望  真的
More, more than we hoped for, really.
同时也下了更多的功夫  毫无疑问
And, er, more work, that's for sure.
你抓住了每一个机会
You really embraced every opportunity.
我们为你感到骄傲  儿子
We're very proud of you, son.
为你人生中的下个篇章感到十分的骄傲和激动
Very proud and very excited with this next chapter in your life.
干杯
Cheers!
-祝你成功  -抱歉打扰了
- To success! - Excuse me guys?
你们还在等人吗  不然我把这个盘子撤了
Are you still waiting on someone? Or can I take this plate away?
-是的  可以撤下去了  -不  放这吧
- Yeah, you can take it away. - No no no, you can leave it.
不  拿走吧
No, take it.
我想放在这  谢谢
I'd like to keep it. Thank you.
你不会真的认为他会出现吧
You don't really think he will turn up, do you?
好了  别说了  儿子
No, just leave it, son.
这酒很好喝
That's a nice one.
确实不错  这酒是本地的特产
Yeah it's a good one. This one's a local one.
曼塔希
Mantosh?
抱歉  我没有去吃午餐
Sorry, I didn't meet lunch.
你是去读什么课程来着
What's that course again?
酒店管理
Hotel Management.
所以到时候你会去干什么
So you're going when to do what?
管理酒店吗
Manage a hotel!
祝你愉快
Have fun!
你有什么账单需要付吗
Any bills you need to pay?
你学成回来后可以给我们一份工作
You can give us a job when you come back.
我不在家的时候  能不能别乱来
Please could you not do anything while I'm away?
那会让妈妈更加伤心的
That's going to make mum more unhappy than you already do.
伙计
Mate...
你觉得我为什么会离开家
Why do you think I stay away?
墨尔本
我们视自己为酒店管理学校中的联合国
We see ourselves as United Nations of hospitality schools.
我们倾向于认为
And we'd like to think
我们倡导的是一种全球化  均衡化的观念
we teach a global and balanced perspective.
你们来到这里  是因为你们怀有梦想
You're here because you have a dream.
我们的存在  就是为了帮助你们实现梦想
We're here to help make that dream a reality.
是的  我明确地看到酒店行业
Yeah and I saw firsthand how the hospitality industry
可以为有需要的社区提供基础设施
can really bring infrastructure to communities that need it.
但我也看到了它们造成的许多问题
But I also saw a lot of problems that they cause,
也正因此  社区团体
which is why community groups need to be,
需要全程参与
involved every step of the way,
他们也应该受到重视
and they need to be taken seriously.
然后
And?
我想帮助
I guess I want to help
推动这件事  帮他们发声
facilitate that and help give them a voice.
萨罗
Saroo.
我想经营酒店  好把利润都赚进自己口袋里
I want to run hotels, so I put all the profits into my pocket.
先说说你来自哪里吧  好吗
Well, let's start with where you are from? Shall we?
你出生在澳大利亚吗
So, born in Australia?
是  不是...
Yeah No, er...
加尔各答
Calcutta.
我有家人在加尔各答  我的表亲们特别糟糕
I've got family in Calcutta. My cousins are quite bad.
哪个地区
Which part?
我是被领养的  我不算是印度人
I'm adopted. I'm not really Indian.
但是你喜欢板球  对吧
But you like cricket though, right?
你喜欢板球啊
Ah, you like cricket...
你支持澳洲队还是印度队
You go for the Aussies or the Indians?
只支持澳洲队
Only the Aussies, mate!
这就有意思了
This is going to be interesting.
好了  萨罗
Okay, Saroo...
你为什么选这门课
Why did you choose this course?
你还希望从中获得什么
What else do you want to get out of it?
-你好  -你好
- Hi. - Hey!
抱歉
Sorry.
-欢迎  -请进  请进
- Welcome. - Come in. Come in.
你好
Hi!
嗨  你好吗
Hi, how are you?
你们喜欢吃印度菜吗
Do you guys like Indian food?
只准备了印度菜  只有这些
That's all we have. That's all we have.
-闻起来好香啊  -我试着学别人...
- It smells so great. - I tried to copy someone...
你有没有跳过宝莱坞舞蹈
You've ever done Bollywood dance?
-只动一条腿这样  -对  一条腿
- Oh, just like, one leg. - Yeah, one leg...
比如我说"手电筒"  用你们的语言怎么说
Okay, well, like, I say flashlight. What do you say?
-口袋灯  -口袋灯[法语]
- Lampo de poche. - Lampo de poche?
-口袋灯  -手电筒的说法...
- Lampo de poche. - Flashlight is er...
你们怎么叫
What do you say?
电筒
Torch.
如果你想用手抓着吃
If you want to eat with your hands,
就要用馕盛着  像勺子一样
you need to use the naan, like a spoon.
-用叉子吧  -不  让他用馕
- Use a fork. - No, let him use the naan.
你们怎么说的士
So how do you say taxi?
-的士  -的士
- Taxi. - Taxi.
这个词在所有语言里都一样
It is the same in every language.
你想用叉子吗  萨罗
Do you want a fork, Saroo?
好啊
Yeah!
他像我父亲一样
He's like my father.
-你要不要再来一瓶啤酒  -要  谢谢
- You want another beer? - Yes please, thank you.
古度  我想吃糖耳朵
Guddu, I want some jalebi.
你好啊
Hello...
你没事吧
You okay?
萨罗
Saroo?
我并不是来自加尔各答
I'm not from Calcutta.
我迷路了
I'm lost.
豪拉火车站很大  你当时一定吓坏了
Howrah station is enormous, you must have been freaking out.
有一次我去布里朝圣  经过那里
I once went through there on a pilgrimage to Puri,
结果我两次没赶上火车
and I missed my connection twice.
你那时候不会说孟加拉语吗
And you didn't speak Bengali?
我当时连那种语言叫什么都不知道
I didn't even know it was called that.
-你在火车上待了多长时间  -好几天吧
- How long were you on the train? - A couple of days.
好几天吗
A couple of days?
萨罗  你的家乡在哪里来着
Saroo, what was your hometown again?
甘尼斯塔莱
Ganestlay.
我一定是记错了  因为没有这个地方
I must have had it wrong because it doesn't exist.
但你一定还记得别的线索吧
But there must be something else that you do remember.
那个站台
The platform...
我睡着的地方  有一个很大的雨水收集箱
I fell asleep on, there's a big rain tank.
那里离甘尼斯塔莱只有几站路
It was only a few stops from Ganestlay.
成千上万的火车站都有雨水收集箱
There are thousands of stations with rain tanks.
好吧  这是很久以前的事了
Okay, it was a long time ago.
你有没有听说过一个新项目  叫谷歌地球
Have you heard of this new program, Google Earth?
它很神奇  可以帮你找到世界上任何一个地方
It's incredible, you can find any place from anywhere.
听我说  我们可以查出
Listen to me, we can find
当时客运列车的时速是多少
out how fast passenger trains went back then.
我们用那个时速
We take that speed,
乘以你坐火车的小时数
multiply by the hours that you were on the train.
就成了
That's it!
我们能得出搜索半径
We create a search radius.
然后在这范围内  找出那个有雨水收集箱的车站
And inside there, you will find the station with the rain tank.
没错  可是搜索印度
Yeah, but it will take a
所有的火车站  要花上一辈子的时间
lifetime to search all the stations in India.
我有说所有的火车站吗
Did I say all the stations?
好吧  哪怕只找一半
Ok, even half the stations.
各位  我真的不想谈论这件事
Really guys, I don't want to talk about this.
你的父母有找过你吗
Did your parents try to find you?
-怎么了  -他们当然找过他
- What? - They tried to find him.
不  我的意思是
No I just mean like,
如果他们找过你  可能会留下书面线索
if they tried to find him, maybe they left like a paper trail.
什么书面线索
What paper trail?
-他连自己姓什么都不知道  -我妈不识字
- He didn't know his surname. - My mum couldn't read or write.
她做什么工作的
What does she do?
劳工  她抬石块的
A labourer, she carried rocks.
你妈妈吗
Your mum?
我妈大约四年前去世了
My mom died about four years ago now.
我很遗憾
I'm sorry.
我爸爸还是很生她的气
My dad is still so angry at her.
当然不是因为她病了
Not for getting sick, obviously...
而是因为她不肯做化疗
but just for refusing chemo.
但她很了解自己  清楚自己想要的生活方式
But she just knew herself, you know? She knew what her terms were
以及如何度过余下的时间  所以...
and she knew how she wanted to live, so...
大概就是无法接受吧
Just couldn't accept that, I guess.
那你又是什么感觉
And how do you feel?
我很想她
I just miss her.
你觉得巴拉特关于搜索半径那个提议怎么样
And what do you think of Bharat's search radius idea?
那是什么意思
What was that?
这是你的舞步吗  你是这样跳舞的吗
Is that your dance? Is that how you dance?
天啊
Oh, God!
客运列车速度
塔斯马尼亚岛  霍巴特
你不能再这样下去了
You can't keep going on like this.
让我来帮你
Let me help you.
我们去跑步吧
Let's go for a run.
什么
What?
露西
Lucy!
过来
Come here.
等一下
Hold on.
抽筋了
Got a cramp.
你骗我  你作弊
You lied! You cheat.
我从来没给别人看过这个
I never show anybody this.
为什么  很美啊
Why? They're beautiful.
我真的很喜欢画画  这是我的小爱好
I do enjoy it. My little hobby.
看看曼塔希啊
Oh wow, look at Mantosh!
他今晚会来  我真的很高兴
I'm so glad he's coming tonight.
狂妄无礼的小东西
Cheeky little thing.
精力十足
Pure energy.
但是很了不起
But incredible.
真有爱
So sweet!
他一向难以控制  可是
He's been hard to control, but...
却非常聪明
very, very smart... and very...
只要他能学会控制自己  他做什么都能成功
I mean, he could do anything if he just learned to control that energy.
他任何事情都能做到
He could do it, and do it all.
萨罗对他的保护欲很强
Saroo is very protective of him.
我很幸运
I've been blessed.
非常幸运
Very blessed.
你妈妈给我看了你以前那些奖杯
Your mom showed me all your old little trophies.
妈妈  你不是吧
Mum, you didn't.
我都不知道你以前那么喜欢运动
I didn't know you were so athletic.
那些只是一半而已  还有很多在车库里
That's only half of them. There's plenty more in the garage.
你去哪儿  伙计
Hey, where you going, mate?
把烟抽完
Finishing my smoke.
现在我想让他离开沙发
I can barely get him off...
-都很难  -露西
- ...the couch these days. - Lucy!
你为什么就不能告诉他们
Why can't you just tell them...
-你最近在干什么  -不要说
- what you've been up to? - Don't!
告诉我们
Tell us.
他们会理解和支持你
They will understand and they will support you.
什么事  快说吧
What? Come on.
嘿  吃晚餐了
Hey, um, dinner!
赶快趁热吃吧
Better eat it, while it's hot.
-你饿了吗  -是的
- You hungry? - Yeah.
怎么了
What?
我错过了什么
What have I missed?
没什么
Nothing.
-她看起来不高兴  -她没有不高兴
- She looks upset. - She's not upset!
你又不知道我的感受
You don't know how I feel.
萨罗无所不知
Saroo knows everything.
他可是专家
He's an expert.
他是个经理
He's a manager.
你为什么来这里
Why are you here?
因为他是你的兄弟
He's here because he's your brother.
不  他不是
No, he's not.
-我们不一样  -住口  萨罗
- We're different. - Hey, now now, Saroo!
萨罗
Saroo...
好了
All right.
没事的
It's all right.
别这样
Hey hey, no no...
没事了  没事了  停下
It's all right, It's all right... Stop!
不要动
Don't move.
没事了
It's okay.
干得好啊
Nice one, mate.
没事了  没事了  深呼吸  深呼吸
It's okay mate, It's okay, just breathe, mate. Just breathe...
我恨他对你造成的伤害
I hate what he's done to you.
对不起
I'm sorry.
萨罗
Saroo!
Saroo.
萨罗
Saroo!
吻我
Kiss me.
别这样  求你了
Stop, please.
看着我
Look at me.
Look at me!
-晚点再谈  行吗  -你魂不守舍的
- Can this wait? - Where are you?
能不能等我们回家再谈
Can this wait 'til we get home?
-行吗  -家
- Yah? - Home?
什么家
What home?
你是指我独自待在一个房间
You mean, where I'm alone
你独自待在另一个房间的那个地方吗
in one room and you're alone in another room?
来啊
Come on.
别这样  露西
Stop, Luce. Stop it.
来啊
Come on.
求你了
Please.
萨罗
Saroo!
你必须面对现实
You need to face reality!
你说的现实是什么意思
What do you mean? Reality?
你能想象我的心情吗  知道自己亲哥哥
You have any idea what it's like knowing my real brother...
和母亲每一天都在找我
and mother spend everyday of their lives looking for me?
我的亲哥哥每天怎样呼喊着我的名字
How every day my real brother screams my name!
你能想象
Can you imagine the pain
他们不知道我的下落的痛苦吗
they must be in for not knowing where I am?
25年  露西  25年了
25 years, Luce. 25!
你为什么不告诉我这些心结
Why didn't you tell me that's was happening for you?
我们在优越的生活中  放纵享受着
And we swung about in our privileged lives.
那让我觉得恶心
It makes me sick.
我必须找到家
I have to find home.
他们必须知道  好吗
They need to know, okay?
我从未阻拦过你
I've never stopped you.
我想帮忙
I want to help.
我不能再这样下去了
I can't do this anymore.
你值得更好的
You deserve more.
别这样
Don't you do that!
你不能这样  这都是你错  可不怪我
Don't you dare do that! This is on you, not on me.
萨罗  你在吗  伙计
Saroo, you there, mate?
明天是单日国际板球赛
It's One Day International tomorrow.
你想来的话就来吧
You can come over if you like?
我是想告诉你  我修好了船柄
I meant to tell you, I fixed the tiller.
我们为什么不带它出去  我们可以开去海岸
Why don't we take her out? We can head up the coast?
嘿  萨罗
Hey, Saroo...
伙计  你妈妈她不...
Mate, your mum's not, um,
听着  我们找不到曼塔希  他又失踪了
look, we've lost track of Mantosh, he's missing again.
你知道她有多担心
You know how worried she gets.
我们知道你辞了工作  伙计
We know you quit your job, mate.
我们很担心你  儿子
Just worried about you, son.
我最近时不时就去看看它
I've been visiting her.
每天晚上我顺着那些街道走回家
Every night I walk those streets home.
从坝上走回家
Home from the dam.
从车站走回家
Home from the station.
我现在知道了...
I know now...
路上走的每一步
...every single step of the way.
我想象着...
And I imagine that I'm...
我在它耳旁轻语
...whispering in her ear...
我在这  没事了
I'm here, it's alright.
她是什么样的
What was she like?
很美
Beautiful.
纽约怎么样
How was New York?
都一样
It's the same.
所以  你为什么回来了
So, what brings you back?
我拿到经费了
My funding came through.
太棒了
It's great!
看吧
See...
他们知道你有多棒
They know how good you are.
我很想你
I miss you.
我见到你妈妈了
I saw your mom.
她不是很好
She's not doing very well.
我担心  如果我告诉她我在找家她会崩溃的
I'm worried, it would kill her if she knew I was searching.
你低估她了
You underestimate her.
她需要你
She needs you.
不  给我5卢比  我把这些都搬走
No, give me five rupees then I'll carry them all
好吧  你赢了  拿着吧
Okay, you win, take this
他当时搬着西瓜  没看到车过来
He was carrying a watermelon and didn't see it coming
怎么了
What?
如果你找到了家  他们却都不在了怎么办
What if you do find home and they're not even there?
你还会不停地去搜寻吗
And you never stop and keep searching?
你不知道过了这么久发生了什么
And you don't know what happens over time,
世事变迁  整个世界都在变
things change, and entire worlds change.
我别无选择
I don't have a choice.
留下来
Stay.
我不能
I can't.
站在那别过来
Stay right there
你不是应该照顾好他的吗
Weren't you supposed to look after him?
你去哪了
Where were you?
你不爱他了吗
Don't you love him?
约翰和曼塔希乘船出去了
John heard Mantosh is out on the boats.
去抓龙虾了
Doing a lobster run.
他明天回来
He's due back tomorrow.
所以他会赚很多的现金  又要整天喝酒了
So he'll be flushed with cash, back on the hard stuff.
我很抱歉你不能有自己的孩子
I'm sorry you couldn't have your own kids.
你说什么
What are you saying?
我们
We...
并不是白纸一张
weren't blank pages, were we?
像你亲生的孩子那样
Like your own would have been.
你领养的不只是我们  也领回了我们的过去
You weren't just adopting us but our past as well.
-我感觉我们在害死你  -我可以生孩子的
- I feel like, we're killing you. - I could have had kids.
什么
What?
我们选择不生孩子
We chose not to have kids.
我们想要你们两个
We wanted the two of you.
那才是我们想要的
That's what we wanted.
我们想要你们两个出现在我们的生活里
We wanted the two of you in our lives.
那是我们的选择
That's what we chose.
那也是我爱上你爸爸的原因之一
That's one of the reasons, I fell in love with your dad.
因为我们都觉得
Because we both felt, as if...
这世界上的人已经够多了
... the world has enough people in it.
生个孩子  并不保证任何事会变得更美好
Have a child, couldn't guarantee it will make anything better.
但是接受一个像你们这样处于困境的孩子
But to take a child that's suffering like you boys were.
给你们一个机会
Give you a chance in the world.
那意义非凡
That's something.
我猜你们从来没想过会有这么困难
I bet you never imagined it being this hard.
这并不是困难的问题
It's not a matter of hard.
这不是...
It's not a mat...
我只有这一条路可以走
There's only one path for me.
我是这么想的
And, that's how I think.
之所以会这样是因为...
That's how this happened because...
在我岁12的时候
When I was 12,
我看到过一个幻象
I had a vision.
有些人会说那是精神崩溃  但是...
Some people would say, it was a breakdown. But it...
我父亲是个酒鬼  你知道的  就好像
My dad was an alcoholic. You know that, and he was like
他不是一个好人
he wasn't a good man.
他那时失去了理智
He was out of control when I was...
而我当时站在屋后
I was standing at the back of the house.
我眺望着田野
I was looking out across this field.
希望这世界将我吞没
And I just wanted the earth to swallow me up.
我...
And I...
我感受到一股电流  像是被电了一下
I felt an electric current, it was like a shock,
好像我浑身上下都在震颤
like a jolt through my whole body.
后来我看见...
And then I saw...
一个棕色皮肤的孩子
a brown skinned child
穿过田野
across that field.
他站在我的身边
And he was standing beside me.
就在那里  我很强烈地感觉到了
And it was right there and I could feel it so strongly.
我人生中第一次感受到了美好的东西
And for the first time in my life I felt something good...
我感觉很愉快
I felt good.
我知道那是在指引我
And I knew it was guiding me.
我知道我会没事的
And I knew that I was going to be fine.
那一刻我仿佛看到了我的未来  就在眼前
It was, as if, that moment I could see my future, right there!
因为我一直以为我可以把这个家聚在一起
Because I always thought that I could keep this family together.
现在...
And now...
现在我也不知道了
Now I don't know.
哪里...
Where...
-妈妈  -这是怎么回事  我不明白
- Mum... - What's happening? I don't understand.
你再也不跟我谈心了
You don't talk to me any more.
我需要你  萨罗
I need you, Saroo.
曼塔希
Mantosh!
我为我晚餐时说得话道歉
Sorry for what I said at dinner.
甘尼希塔莱
Ganesh Talai...
Ganesh Talai.
甘尼斯塔莱
Ganestlay!
妈妈
Mum
我找到家了
I found home!
什么
What?
请你一定要等我
Please wait for me.
我在这
I'm here.
原来你一直就是在做这件事
So this is where you've been.
我不想让你觉得我忘恩负义
I don't want you to feel, I was ungrateful.
我无时无刻不想告诉你
There wasn't a day, I didn't want to tell you.
萨罗
Saroo.
我真的希望她还在那等你
I really hope she's there.
她需要看看你长得多么漂亮
She needs to see how beautiful you are!
印度  坎德瓦
你好  我以前住在这里
Hi, I used to live here.
我..过去...
I...used to...
有什么要帮忙的吗
Can I help?
这是我  我是萨罗
That's me. I'm Saroo.
我以前住在这里
I used to live here.
-你住这吗  -是的  我以前住在这
- You lived here? - Yes I used to live here.
我在找古度  卡鲁  夏绮拉
I'm looking for Guddu, Kallu, Shekila.
我的妈妈
My mother.
跟我来
Come.
去哪
Come where?
跟我来
Come with me.
来就是了
Just come.
萨罗
Saroo?
妈妈
Mum.
萨罗
Saroo?
Saroo...
萨罗
Saroo!
我找你找得好辛苦
Oh, how I looked for you!
萨罗
Saroo!
对不起
I'm sorry.
真的对不起
I'm so sorry.
是的  西瓜
Yes, the watermelon.
西瓜
Tarabuja!
西瓜  没错  西瓜
Tarabuja! Yes, tarabuja!
西瓜
Watermelon...
古度呢
And Guddu?
古度在哪
Where is Guddu?
他在哪
Where is he?
古度不在了
Guddu is no more.
他进入天堂了
He is with God.
这是夏绮拉
Shekila.
夏绮拉
Shekila?
-夏绮拉  -他是你哥哥
- Shekila? - He's your brother!
她长这么大了
She's so big!
是我  萨罗
It's me, Saroo.
真美
Beautiful.
你好  妈妈
Hi, mum.
我知道你已经睡着了
I know you will be sound asleep.
我只是想报个平安
I just want to say that I'm safe.
我平安无事  疑惑也都解开了
I'm safe and the questions have been answered.
不再是死胡同了
There are no more dead-ends.
我找到了我的亲生母亲
I found my mother, and...
她很感谢你们二位抚养我长大
she thanks you both for raising me.
她明白你们是我的家人
She understands that you are my family.
她知道我还活着  就很开心了
She's... happy, just knowing I'm alive.
我找到了她  但这不会改变你的身份
I found her, but that doesn't change who you are.
我爱你  妈妈
I love you mum...
十分爱你
so much.
还有你  爸爸
And you, Dad.
还有曼塔希
And Mantosh.
快来
C'mon!
我们走
Let's go!
快来
Come on!
萨罗
Saroo!
我们走
Let's go!
走快点
Walk faster!
我要走了  我要走了  我要走了
I'm going, I'm going, I'm going!
你会掉下去的
Oh, you're gonna fall!
萨罗·布莱尔利于2012年二月12日回到了甘尼希塔莱
他失踪在外超过25年
25年前  就在他踏上那节空车厢的当晚
他的哥哥古度也去世了  在站台附近被一列火车撞死
萨罗的母亲卡姆拉  从未放弃过相信萨罗会回来
所以她从未搬过家
卡姆拉说当她儿子回来时  她震惊得"如遭雷击"
她心中的幸福感"深似海洋"
萨罗得知  多年前  作为5岁的小孩
他一直把自己的名字拼错了
他的真名叫"瑟卢"  意思是...
雄狮
-萨罗  -古度
- Saroo. - Guddu.
甘尼希塔莱
每年印度有超过8万名儿童失踪
我们正在跟一些杰出的组织合作  帮助印度和全世界的儿童
请登录影片官网查看本片是如何帮助了流浪儿
欢迎加入我们  一起让世界更美好